<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
    xmlns:math="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xml:id="zibaldone">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Zibaldone di Pensieri</title>
                <author xml:id="G.L.">Giacomo Leopardi</author>
                <respStmt>
                   <resp>Encoder of English version</resp>
                    <name xml:id="A.H.">Atousa Heidarnia</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>ZdP Project;</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bologna</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author ref="#G.L.">Giacomo Leopardi</author>
                    <title>Zibaldone di pensieri</title>
                    <editor xml:id="R.D.">Rolando Damiani</editor>
                    <publisher>Mondadori</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Milano</pubPlace>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </bibl>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Napoli</settlement>
                        <repository>Biblioteca Nazionale (BNN)</repository>
                        <idno>Carte Leopardi, C.L._V.1</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                </msDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Canti">
                        <author ref="#G.L.">Giacomo Leopardi</author>
                        <title ref="#Canti">Canti</title>
                        <editor>Gavazzeni</editor>
                        <pubPlace>Firenze</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Accademia della Crusca</publisher>
                        <date>2009</date>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Av_Fabulae">
                        <author ref="#Aviano">Flavio Aviano</author>
                        <title ref="#Av_Fabulae"> Fabulae cum adnotationibus. Ad usum Seminarii
                            Patavini </title>
                        <pubPlace>Bologna</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Stamperia dell'Istituto delle scienze</publisher>
                        <date>1787</date>
                    </bibl>
                    <biblStruct xml:id="Operette">
                        <analytic>
                            <title>Prose</title>
                            <editor ref="#R.D.">Rolando Damiani</editor>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <author ref="#G.L.">Giacomo Leopardi</author>
                            <title ref="#Operette">Operette Morali</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Mondadori i Meridiani</publisher>
                                <date>1988</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <bibl>
                        <author xml:id="E.D.">Elio Donato</author>
                        <title xml:id="Vita">Vita Vergilii</title>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Epistolario">
                        <author ref="#G.L.">Giacomo Leopardi</author>
                        <title ref="#Epistolario">Epistolario</title>
                        <editor>Franco Brioschi, Patrizia Landi</editor>
                        <pubPlace>Torino</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Bollati Boringhieri</publisher>
                        <date>1998</date>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Pittori">
                        <author ref="#Dati">Carlo Roberto Dati</author>
                        <title ref="#Pittori">Vite de' Pittori Antichi</title>
                    </bibl>
              
                    <bibl xml:id="Opere_Algarotti">
                        <author ref="#Algarotti">Algarotti</author>
                        <title ref="#Opere_Algarotti">Opere</title>
                        <pubPlace>Cremona</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1778">1778</date>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Prosepoesie">
                        <author ref="#G.L."> Giacomo Leopardi </author>
                        <title ref="#ProsePoesie"> Tutte le poesie e tutte le prose </title>
                        <editor> Emanuele Trevi e Lucio Felici </editor>
                        <pubPlace> Roma </pubPlace>
                        <publisher> Newton Compton </publisher>
                        <date> 1997 </date>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Institutiones_Oratoriae">
                        <author ref="#Quintiliano">Quintiliano</author>
                        <title ref="#Institutiones_Oratoriae">Institutiones Oratoriae</title>
                        <pubPlace>Leida</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1665">1665</date>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Beau_Physique">
                        <author ref="#Camper"> Petrus Camper</author>
                        <title ref="#Beau_Physique"> Discours sur le moyen de répresenter les
                            passions que se manifestent sur le visage. Sur la conformité entre
                            l’hommes et les animaux et sur le Beau phisique</title>
                        <pubPlace>Utrecht</pubPlace>
                        <date when="17992">1792</date>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Bacchides">
                        <author ref="#Plauto">Plauto</author>
                        <title ref="#Baccides">Bacchides</title>
                        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1619">1619</date>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Rudens">
                        <author ref="#Plauto">Plauto</author>
                        <title ref="#Rudens">Bacchides</title>
                        <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1619">1619</date>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Vita_Alfieri">
                        <author ref="#Alfieri">Vittorio Alfieri</author>
                        <title ref="Vita_Alfieri">Vita di Vittorio Alfieri da Asti scritta da
                            esso</title>
                        <pubPlace>boh</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1806">1806</date>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Annali_di_scienze_e_lettere">
                        <author ref="#Borsieri">Pietro Borsieri</author>
                        <title/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Del_Sublime">
                        <author ref="#Longino">Pseudo Longino</author>
                        <title ref="#Del_Sublime">Trattato del Sublime, tradotto dal greco</title>
                        <editor>Antonfrancesco Gori</editor>
                        <pubPlace>Bologna</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1748">1748</date>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="Ragion_Poetica">
                        <author ref="#Gravina">Gianvincenzo Gravina</author>
                        <title ref="#Ragion_Poetica">Della ragion poetica</title>
                        <pubPlace>Napoli</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1731">1731</date>
                    </bibl>

                </listBibl>
                <listPerson>
                    <person xml:id="Ariosto">
                        <persName type="pers_citata" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/71386455"
                            ref="https://www.treccani.it/enciclopedia/ludovico-ariosto_%28Dizionario-Biografico%29/"
                            > Ludovico Ariosto</persName>
                    </person>
          
                  <person xml:id="Dante">
                        <persName type="pers_citata" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/97105654"
                            ref="https://www.treccani.it/enciclopedia/dante-alighieri_%28Dizionario-Biografico%29/"
                            > Dante Alighieri </persName>
                    </person>
                  
          
                 
                    <person xml:id="Longino">
                        <persName type="pers_citata" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/42634532"
                            ref="https://www.treccani.it/enciclopedia/cassio-longino_%28Enciclopedia-Italiana%29/"
                            >Longino Cassio </persName>
                    </person>
                   
                    
                    <person xml:id="Breme">
                        <persName type="pers_citata" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/56672363"
                            ref="https://www.treccani.it/enciclopedia/ludovico-pietro-arborio-gattinara-dei-conti-di-sartirana-dei-marchesi-di-breme_%28Dizionario-Biografico%29/"
                            > Ludovico Pietro Arborio Gattinara dei conti di Sartirana dei marchesi
                            di Breme </persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Petrarca">
                        <persName type="pers_citata" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/39382430"
                            ref="https://www.treccani.it/enciclopedia/francesco-petrarca_%28Dizionario-Biografico%29/"
                            >Francesco Petrarca</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Testi">
                        <persName type="pers_citata" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/73902706"
                            ref="https://www.treccani.it/enciclopedia/fulvio-testi_(Dizionario-Biografico)"
                            >Fulvio Testi</persName>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Filicaia">
                        <persName type="pers_citata" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/2565277"
                            ref="https://www.treccani.it/enciclopedia/vincenzo-filicaia_(Dizionario-Biografico)"
                            > Vincenzo Filicaia </persName>
                    </person>
                 
                </listPerson>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
   <text type="20">
      <body>
         <pb xml:id="p_20" n="20"/>
         <p> <persName ref="#Breme">Breme</persName> Breme has forgotten that philosophical observation, old though it is, that <lb/>the simplest, truest, and surest means are always the last that men discover, <lb/>and so it is in the arts and the professions, as in the ordinary things of life, and <lb/>in everything. And so the last thing achieved by someone who feels and wants <lb/> to express the emotions of his heart, etc., is simplicity and naturalness, and the <lb/>first thing is artifice and affectation, and someone who has not studied and has <lb/>not read and is, as these people say, immune to the prejudices of art, and in<lb/>nocent, etc., certainly does not write with simplicity, but quite the opposite. <lb/>We see it in young children when they begin to compose: they do not write
            with simplicity and naturalness at all, for, if that were the case, the best writ<lb/>ings
            would be those of children, whereas, on the contrary, one sees only exag<lb/>gerations
            and affectations and refi nements, albeit clumsy ones, and the simplicity
            that is there is not simplicity but childishness. You could say the same thing
            about certain popular songs, etc. etc., which, in a certain sense, are simple, but
            put a little of that simplicity alongside Anacreon’s, which seems unsurpass<lb/>able,
            and see whether you think it can still be called simplicity. Hence the aim
            of art, which these people criticize, is not art at all but nature, and the height of
            art is naturalness and the concealment of art, which novices and the ignorant
            are unable to conceal, even though they have very little of it, but that very little
            shines through, and the cruder it is, the more nauseating. And Horace’s nine
            years,1 which Breme ridicules, were certainly not spent increasing the artifice
            of his writing, but in reducing it, or, rather, in increasing it in order to conceal
            it, and in other words to come ever closer to nature, which is the aim of all
            those studies and those emendations, etc., which Breme mocks, which the
            Romantics mock, contradicting themselves, because,</p>
      </body>
   </text>
            <text type="21">
                <body>
                   <pb xml:id="p_21" n="21"/><p>they curse art
                      and extol nature, they fail to realize that where there is less art, there is less
                      nature.</p>
                   <p xml:id="p21_1" n="21.1"> The poet must not only imitate and depict nature perfectly but also imitate
                      and depict it naturally; indeed, he who does not imitate nature naturally does
                      not imitate nature.That’s why <persName ref="#Ovid">Ovid</persName>, who depicts nature without naturalness,
                      that is, who pursues those objects to such an extent that in the end he presents
                      them to us, and even enables us to see and touch and feel them, but only after
                      infinite labor on his part (so that he needs a page to show us what<persName ref="#Dante">Dante</persName>shows
                    us in a terzina), and with more tenacity than effi cacy, soon becomes tiresome
                      and, what’s more, unpleasing, because he is unable to conceal his art, and with
                      so much circling around the objects (not only because of rash intemperance
                      and restlessness but also because he is unable to describe the figure without a
                      lot of details, and if he were not lengthy he would not be clear) he displays dili<lb/>gence,
                      and diligence in poets is the opposite of naturalness. What poets must
                      seem to display, besides the objects imitated, is a beautiful negligence, and this
                      is what we see in the ancients, who were masters of this most necessary and
                      essential art, this is what we see in <persName ref="#Ariosto">Ariosto</persName>,<persName ref="#Petrarca"
                         >Petrarca</persName>,etc., this is what is lack<lb/>ing
                      unfortunately even in the best and most classic of the moderns, this is what
                      is not achieved through sentimentality, or through  <persName ref="#Breme">Breme</persName>’s system, or in mod<lb/>ern
                      French poetry, nor can it be achieved, because this very sentimentality re<lb/>veals
                      a certain diligence, etc., it reveals, in short, the poet who is speaking, etc.
                   </p>
                   <p xml:id="p21_2" n="21.2">In <persName ref="#Ovid">Ovid</persName> we see, in short, that he wants to depict and do what is so difficult
                      with words, to show the fi gure, etc., and we see the work he puts into it. In
                      <persName ref="#Dante">Dante</persName> no: he seems to want to tell a story and do what is easy with words, and
                      in the way that words are ordinarily used, and he describes exquisitely, and yet
                      the work he puts into it cannot be seen, he doesn’t point out this or that little
                      detail, and he raised his hand and shook it and turned a little and so forth (as
                      the Romantics do in their descriptions, and in general those En glish or French
                      descriptive poets, as well as prose, etc., lately so much in vogue). In short, in
                      <persName ref="#Dante">Dante</persName> there is negligence, in <persName ref="#Ovid">Ovid</persName> not.</p>
                      
            <p xml:id="p21_3" n="21.3"><seg source="#Quiete2">
                    <l>Sì come dopo la procella oscura<lb/> Canticchiando gli augelli escon del
                        loco<lb/> Dove cacciogli il vento (nembo) e la paura;<lb/></l>
                    <l>E il villanel che presso al paterno foco<lb/> Sta sospirando il sol, si
                        riconforta (si rasserena)<lb/> Sentendo il dolce canto e il dolce
                        gioco</l>
                </seg>
               <seg source="#en.translate">
                  <l>[As after the dark tempest
                     <lb/>Birds singing leave the place
                     <lb/>Where wind (storm) and fear drove them;
                  </l>
                  <l>And the villager at his hearth
                     <lb/>Yearning for the sun, is comforted (is cheered)
                     <lb/>By the sound of sweet song and sweet merriment;]1</l>
               </seg>
            </p>
                   <p xml:id="p21_4" n="21.4"> The great majority of useful works bring plea sure indirectly, showing how
                      <lb/>we can obtain it. Poetry brings it immediately, provides it for us.</p>
            <p xml:id="p21_5" n="21.5">
                <seg source="#Dialogo_Murco_Filosofo"><persName
                   ref="#Longinus">Longinus</persName>asked (at the end of his treatise On the Sublime) why there were
                   so few great men in his time and gave the explanation that it was partly be<lb/>cause
                   of the end of the republics and of liberty, and partly because of avarice,
                   lust, and sloth.Now these are not the mothers but the sisters of that effect of
                   which we speak. And they all derive from the progress of reason and civiliza<lb/>tion,
                   and from the absence or weakening of illusions, without which there will
                   almost never be greatness of thought, or power and force and boldness of
                   spirit, or great actions, which are usually a kind of madness. But when every<lb/>one
                   is thoroughly enlightened as to how glory, patriotism, liberty, etc. etc., are
                   vain delights and goods without substance, he looks for something solid, ob<lb/>scene
                   carnal pleasures,etc.
                </seg>
            </p>
                </body>
           
            </text>
            <text type="22">
                <body>
                    <pb xml:id="p_22" n="22"/><p>
                       in other words earthly pleasures, he looks for
                       personal benefit whether in money or otherwise, and becomes necessarily
                       selfish, unwilling to make sacrifi ces for imaginary rewards, or to compromise
                      himself for others, or to place at risk a greater asset such as life, property, etc.,
                       for a lesser one, such as praise, etc. (not to mention that civilization makes all
                       men the same, removing and suppressing differences, and the distribution of
                       wisdom and good qualities does not increase the mass but fragments it, so
                     that, reduced to small portions, it produces small effects). This leads to avarice,
                     lust, and sloth, and from them the barbarism that follows the excess of civilizat<lb/>ion.
                       And so there is no doubt that the progress of reason and the extinction of
                    </p>
                </body>
            </text>
            <text type="23">
                <body>
                    <pb xml:id="p_23" n="23"/><p>
                       <persName ref="#Bruto">Bruto</persName> illusions produce barbarism, and an excessively enlightened population cer<lb/>tainly
                       does not become highly civilized, as the philosophers of our day, Mme.
                     de Staël, etc., imagine, but barbarous.1 We are moving fast in this direction
                     and have almost arrived. The greatest enemy of barbarism is not reason but
                       nature. Nature (if properly followed, however) provides us with illusions that,
                       in their right place, make a people truly civilized, and certainly no one would
                       <l/>describe the Romans when they fought the Carthaginians, or the Greeks at
                       Thermopylae, as barbarians, even though, for both populations, it was a time
                      of very powerful illusions and was hardly philosophical at all. Illusions are
                    natural, inherent to the system of the world. When they are removed com<lb/>pletely
                       or almost completely, man is denatured, and every denatured people is
                      barbarous, for things can no longer run as the system of the world requires.
                       Reason is a light; nature seeks to be illuminated by reason, not burned. As I
                       say happened with the Greeks and the Romans: at the time of Longinus, they
                       were already almost barbarous, yet there had been no foreign invasion; barba<lb/>rism
                       arose from their very own land, from those most civilized lands, because
                       civilization had become excessive. Cicero was the advocate of illusions.2 Read
                       in particular the Philippics, but then all of his other po liti cal orations. He is
                       always seeking to persuade the Romans to act in pursuit of their illusions, al<lb/>ways
                       with the example of their forebears, glory, liberty, patriotism, death
                       rather than servitude. What a disgrace is this: Antony, a tyrant of this race, is
                       still alive, etc. And yet, though Antony in other times would have been stabbed
                       in the Forum or in the Curia as a most shameful tyrant, in Rome they could
                       not succeed, even with so many armies against him, and with so much reason
                       to hope that he would be defeated, that he would be declared an enemy of the
                       state; they calculated, sought, etc., what in other times would have been agreed
                       unanimously without a moment’s hesitation. Cicero argued in vain, there were
                       no longer the illusions of earlier times, reason had come, people didn’t give a
                       fig about patriotism glory benefi t to others to posterity, etc.; they had become
                        egoists, they weighed the benefi t to themselves, worried about what might
                        happen, forgot boldness and drive, forgot greatness of spirit, the example of
                      their forebears was a triviality [23] in times so changed. And so they lost their
                       freedom, they were unable to retain and defend what even Brutus had done out
                       of a last vestige of illusion; the emperors came, lust and sloth increased, and
                      shortly afterward, with so much more of philosophy, books, science, experi<lb/>ence,
                       history, they had become barbarous.
                       ,lb/>And reason, by making us naturally inclined to pursue our own advantage,
                       and removing the illusions that bind us to one another, dissolves society absolutely
                       and turns people to savagery.
                    </p>
                <p xml:id="p23_2" n="23.2">
                   It seems that even the love of wonder has to be reduced to love of the extraordinary
                   and hatred of the boredom produced by uniformity.</p>
                <p xml:id="p23_3" n="23.3">
                   <seg source="#Erminia2"><l>Seeing the moon journey with me.</l></seg>
                </p>
                   <p xml:id="p23_4" n="23.4">It is not fanciful but rather reasonable and true to place the heroic periods
                      among the most ancient people. The heroism and self-sacrifice and glorious
                      death, etc., discussed by  <persName
                         ref="Breme">Breme</persName><quote source="#Spettatore_47">Spettatore p.47</quote> end with illusions, and no
                      fool wishes these for himself in a period of reason and philosophy, like the
                      present, one that, as such, is what I have said it is, a period totally devoid of
                      heroism, etc.</p>
                   <p xml:id="p23_5" n="23.5">The only lyric poet, ancient or modern, in whom you find that feeling
                      which inspires eloquence and by dazzling less persuades and moves us more,
                      especially where tenderness is concerned,is <persName ref="#Petrarch,">Petrarch,</persName>,at the very least to that
                      extent. And however superior Horace might be in his images and ideas, in
                      such feeling and eloquence and plentifulness he cannot even approach comparison
                      with Petrarch, whose style (here I am talking not only about the love
                      poems but also particularly and especially about the three lyric poems:<quote source="#RVF_28">O aspettata
                        in ciel beata e bella</quote>, <quote source="#RVF_53">Spirito gentil che quelle
                           membra reggi</quote>, <quote source="#RVF_128">Italia mia</quote> ec.) also has a simplicity and candor all its own, which yet is flexible
                      and admirably fits the nobility and magnificence of the utterance (as in: <quote source="#RVF_28">Pon
                        mente al temerario ardir di Serse</quote> ec.) 
                       both in the whole structure, and continually, and in the various parts and in
                       those passages where he rises to greater sublimity and nobility than usual. His
                       style bends to his ideas (as in: <quote source="#RVF_53"> Rade volte addivien che a l’alte imprese,” etc.
                           [“Rarely it happens that noble ventures</quote> ec.) qventures”]), even if few of any note are to be
                       found in these three poems. It adapts wonderfully to the images that abound in
                       the three poems and which are grafted onto the style and are its lifeblood, etc.(such as: <quote source="#RVF_128">Al qual come si legge, Mario
                           aperse sì ’l fianco</quote> ec. <quote>[Whom, as
                               we read, Marius so wounded]</quote>,<quote>Di lor vene ove il nostro ferro mise</quote> ec.<quote>[With their veins where he plunged our steel]</quote>, <quote
                                   source="#RVF_53">Le man le avess’io avvolte entro i capegli</quote> ec. <quote>[Would that I had my hands clutched in her hair],</quote> etc. </p>
                    <p xml:id="p23_6" n="23.6"> Il <persName ref="#Testi">Testi</persName>Testi’s writing is competently poetic and elegant, not lacking in imagination,
                        and also has some nice little images (as when he says of David: 
                        <quote>E allor
                            che in Oriente il dì nascea / Usciva a pascer l’agne / Su la costa del monte o
                            lungo il rio</quote>[<quote>And when the day dawned in the East he went out to graze his
                                sheep on the mountainside or along the stream]</quote>, in his poem <quote>Nelle squallide spiagge
                                    ove Acheronte </quote>) It has adequate grandeur and some elegance; the
                        ideas, though not new, are neither ill-placed nor ill-stated; he is also fairly successful
                        in his philosophical Canzoni in the style of Horace.He often imitates
                        and sometimes almost translates Horace, but does not have his lively and wellhoned
                        style, or his concise ner vous ness and muscularity and energy and spirit,
                        or great originality or novelty, or what you could really call sublimity in concept
                        and invention. But all the qualities that I have described, save only grandeur
                        and eloquence, shine above all in the Canzoni in the fi rst part, which are  mostly philosophical and Horatian, and in which the style is pure and there is
                        no lack of elegance in manner and concepts. For in the other parts, although
                        they are more exalted and show more strength and eloquence and more powerful
                        descriptions, and are, in short, more reminiscent of Pindar, it is diffi cult to
                        fi nd a canzone that is not smeared roughly and shabbily and visibly and per sistent
                        ly with the tar of his century, which in the fi rst part is just visible here and
                        there as tiny spots, and perhaps one or two canzoni are entirely unblemished by
                        it and might appear to be from another century.His writing also</p>
                </body>
                
            </text>
            <text type="24">
                <body>
                    <pb xml:id="p_24" n="24"/>
                    <p> becomes
                        less elegant and clean, and the words and turns of phrase, meta phors, fi gures
                        of speech are often prosaic. In short, one sees too much of the feverishness and
                        shoddiness and lack of polish of the seventeenth century.Belonging only to Petrarch, as far as feeling is concerned, are not just abundance
                        but also those outbursts full τοῦ πάθους [of pathos] and those affectionate
                        images (such as: <quote>E la povera gente sbigottita </quote>[<quote>And the poor terror- stricken
                            people],</quote>1 etc.) and all else that constitutes true, lively, and spirited eloquence.
                        And from the heart’s infl uence in Petrarch’s poetry comes the softness and
                        unctuousness almost, like that of the smoothest oil, of his Canzoni (and particularly
                        those on Italy). The odes of others seem dry and hard and arid in comparison
                        to his, and while he lacks none of the sublimity that others have, he
                        also has the softness and mellowness that comes from the heart.</p>
                    <p xml:id="p24_2" n="24.2"><persName ref="#Filicaia"
                        >Filicaia</persName> pursues the sublime and also manages to achieve it, but by speaking
                        always of matters pertaining to our Religion he has taken to imitating that
                        supreme sublimity of Scripture, and it is for this supreme sublimity that he is
                        admired. When he does not seek it or does not achieve it, there is almost nothing
                        out of the ordinary about his work, he is never elegant, he has none of
                        Testi’s variety, etc. But even when he achieves that supreme sublimity of style
                        similar to Scripture or prophecy, he is not very pleasing, because of the monotony
                        of his Canzoni and because the impressions of that supreme sublimity
                        are too vehement and therefore cannot last very long and fade away, and the
                        reader becomes inured, so that, with this monotony, the sublime becomes ineffectual
                        and his poems become tedious. The best are the ones on the siege and
                        liberation of Vienna, and among these, in my view, the one that begins <quote>Le
                            corde d’oro elette.</quote> Here and there, they bear the stains of seventeenth- century
                        style. There is no lack of prosaic words, turns of phrase, or meta phors, such as <quote>A tua Pietà m’appello</quote>
                        <quote>[To your Mercy I appeal]</quote> in the first Canzone, and
                        in the second:<quote>E al tuo soldo arrolata è la vittoria</quote><quote>[And in your ser vice is
                            victory enrolled]</quote>.</p>
                </body>
            </text>
          
</TEI>